<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<bible translation="New King James Version" language="English" id="NKJV-EN">
  <book number ="15" name="EZRA and NEHEMIAH">
    <text>
      3. Historical Setting. Aside from Esther, Ezra and Nehemiah are the only historical books of the
      postexilic period, and are of great importance for a reconstruction of the history of postexilic Jewry.
      However, they do not record the history of the people of God in unbroken sequence for the period
      covered by the two books, but only certain parts of it. There are large gaps for which little information is
      available.
      Ezra records, first of all, the return of the Jews from exile under the guidance of Zerubbabel, the
      reorganization of the sacrificial service, and the beginning of the rebuilding of the Temple. All these
      events took place within about two years, early in the reign of Cyrus. During the next 13 years the work
      progressed slowly against opposition. Then appears an account of the resumption of the building of the
      Temple and its completion and dedication under Darius I. Of the next nearly 60 years Ezra leaves no
      record. Then, in 457 B.C., Ezra was sent back to Judea by King Artaxerxes, with far-reaching authority
      to reorganize the nation’s administration according to Mosaic law. He tells of his return and some of his
      reforms, but again breaks the thread of continuity for more than ten years, when Nehemiah appears on
      the scene of action as governor, and reports his activities in the book which bears his name.
      All the events described in Ezra and Nehemiah took place during the first half of the period of the
      Persian Empire, which lasted from 539 B.C., when Babylon fell to the victorious forces of Cyrus, until,
      with the death of Darius III in 331 B.C., the empire ceased to exist and was succeeded by that of
      Alexander the Great. The history of postexilic Jewry begins “in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia”
      (Ezra 1:1). The Persian Empire stretched from the desert wastes of Iran in the east to the coast of Asia
      Minor in the west, and from the Armenian highlands in the north to the border of Egypt in the south.
      Cyrus, its founder, was a prudent and humane monarch. In harmony with his policy of appeasing nations
      subjugated by Babylon, he resettled them in their old homes and restored their places of worship. In
      accord with this generous policy, the Jews were allowed to return to their old homeland and rebuild their
      Temple. For the most part, the kings of Persia attempted to rule their empire with equity and
      consideration. Their officials were admonished to practice honesty and to work in the interests of the
      peoples whom they governed. The monotheistic religion of Zoroaster, the state religion at least from
      Darius I on, stood on a much higher level than that of the polytheistic and idolatrous predecessors of the
      Persians, the people of Babylonia.
      When Cyrus took Babylon he became acquainted with the aged Daniel, trusted counselor of the great
      Nebuchadnezzar of a former era, and learned to appreciate his advice. Through Daniel, Cyrus must have
      become acquainted with Isaiah’s prophecies concerning him and his appointed role in behalf of God’s
      people (Isa. 44:21 to 45:13), and granted their restoration (PK 557). The great work of pacifying his farflung empire in its years of infancy required the king’s full attention. He lost his life in a campaign
      against unruly eastern tribes after a reign of about nine years, counted from the fall of Babylon.
      Returning to Judea, the Jews found hostile neighbors, and were continually harassed by the
      Samaritans, a people of mixed racial and religious origins. Because Cyrus was busy unifying his farflung empire, these enemies succeeded in hindering the Jews and causing them untold trouble that
      slowed the work of rebuilding the Temple.
      Cyrus’ eldest son, Cambyses, reigned for less than eight years. His greatest achievement was the
      conquest of Egypt. That he was favorably disposed toward the Jews is known from a Jewish document
      found in Egypt, but we have no evidence that he actively assisted the Jews in rebuilding their Temple.
      The short reign of the false Smerdis proved a great setback for the Jews. Under this king, described
      by Darius as a destroyer of temples, the work at Jerusalem was stopped. The stoppage may have been
      partly due to Samaritan enemies, for new foundations had to be laid as soon as stable conditions under
      the strong government of Darius I permitted resumption of the work. The era of Darius the Great was
      marked by prosperity and order. The Jews, like other nations, benefited from his wise and strong rule.
      Under the spiritual leadership of the prophets Haggai and Zechariah, they finished the Temple and
      dedicated it in the sixth regnal year of Darius, 515 B.C.
      An era of unrest began, however, when late in his reign Darius decided to invade Greece. From that
      time on the empire experienced repeated reverses in Greece, Egypt, and elsewhere that disturbed the
      internal peace and stability of the empire. The next two kings, Xerxes and Artaxerxes I, were weaklings,
      opportunists, and unstable in character, and owed their throne to the strong hand of powerful counselors.
      Disastrous campaigns in Greece and rebellions in Egypt and other parts of the empire caused great
      unrest and led to vacillating domestic and foreign policies.
      It was during a serious rebellion in Egypt (463–454 B.C.) that Ezra received major concessions for
      the Jews, whose good will Artaxerxes needed in this crucial period, since Judea lay athwart the highway
      to Egypt. Later, when the satrapy to which Judea belonged rebelled (after 450 B.C.), Artaxerxes
      apparently supported the supposedly loyal Samaritans under the erroneous assumption and fear that the
      Jews might join the rebellion. Accordingly Artaxerxes authorized the Samaritans to halt the rebuilding
      of the wall of Jerusalem, which had been in progress for some time. When order in the satrapy was
      restored, Nehemiah, a trusted Jewish court official, succeeded in obtaining a royal appointment as
      governor of Judea, and completed the rebuilding of the city wall. This he did under continuing threats of
      violence.
      He served as governor for two terms, and proved to be an able organizer and religious leader. He laid
      a comparatively solid political, social, and moral foundation that proved of great value in the turbulent
      times that followed.
      4. Theme. Ezra and Nehemiah are historical source books which record the outworking of the divine
      plan in the restoration of the Jews, whereby they were afforded another opportunity to cooperate with
      the eternal purposes and prove their right to exist as a nation. This record shows, furthermore, how the
      prophecies of Isaiah and Jeremiah were fulfilled, and provides invaluable source material by which other
      prophecies, those of Dan. 8 and 9, can securely be anchored to the facts of history.
      Ezra and Nehemiah illustrate, by a series of instructive examples, how a few people can do great
      things for God when led by God-fearing, sincere, unselfish, but fearless and determined leaders. These
      books contain much that edifies and that strengthens faith in the unfailing leadership of God.
    </text>
  </book>
  <book number ="16" name="EZRA and NEHEMIAH">
    <text>
      3. Historical Setting. Aside from Esther, Ezra and Nehemiah are the only historical books of the
      postexilic period, and are of great importance for a reconstruction of the history of postexilic Jewry.
      However, they do not record the history of the people of God in unbroken sequence for the period
      covered by the two books, but only certain parts of it. There are large gaps for which little information is
      available.
      Ezra records, first of all, the return of the Jews from exile under the guidance of Zerubbabel, the
      reorganization of the sacrificial service, and the beginning of the rebuilding of the Temple. All these
      events took place within about two years, early in the reign of Cyrus. During the next 13 years the work
      progressed slowly against opposition. Then appears an account of the resumption of the building of the
      Temple and its completion and dedication under Darius I. Of the next nearly 60 years Ezra leaves no
      record. Then, in 457 B.C., Ezra was sent back to Judea by King Artaxerxes, with far-reaching authority
      to reorganize the nation’s administration according to Mosaic law. He tells of his return and some of his
      reforms, but again breaks the thread of continuity for more than ten years, when Nehemiah appears on
      the scene of action as governor, and reports his activities in the book which bears his name.
      All the events described in Ezra and Nehemiah took place during the first half of the period of the
      Persian Empire, which lasted from 539 B.C., when Babylon fell to the victorious forces of Cyrus, until,
      with the death of Darius III in 331 B.C., the empire ceased to exist and was succeeded by that of
      Alexander the Great. The history of postexilic Jewry begins “in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia”
      (Ezra 1:1). The Persian Empire stretched from the desert wastes of Iran in the east to the coast of Asia
      Minor in the west, and from the Armenian highlands in the north to the border of Egypt in the south.
      Cyrus, its founder, was a prudent and humane monarch. In harmony with his policy of appeasing nations
      subjugated by Babylon, he resettled them in their old homes and restored their places of worship. In
      accord with this generous policy, the Jews were allowed to return to their old homeland and rebuild their
      Temple. For the most part, the kings of Persia attempted to rule their empire with equity and
      consideration. Their officials were admonished to practice honesty and to work in the interests of the
      peoples whom they governed. The monotheistic religion of Zoroaster, the state religion at least from
      Darius I on, stood on a much higher level than that of the polytheistic and idolatrous predecessors of the
      Persians, the people of Babylonia.
      When Cyrus took Babylon he became acquainted with the aged Daniel, trusted counselor of the great
      Nebuchadnezzar of a former era, and learned to appreciate his advice. Through Daniel, Cyrus must have
      become acquainted with Isaiah’s prophecies concerning him and his appointed role in behalf of God’s
      people (Isa. 44:21 to 45:13), and granted their restoration (PK 557). The great work of pacifying his farflung empire in its years of infancy required the king’s full attention. He lost his life in a campaign
      against unruly eastern tribes after a reign of about nine years, counted from the fall of Babylon.
      Returning to Judea, the Jews found hostile neighbors, and were continually harassed by the
      Samaritans, a people of mixed racial and religious origins. Because Cyrus was busy unifying his farflung empire, these enemies succeeded in hindering the Jews and causing them untold trouble that
      slowed the work of rebuilding the Temple.
      Cyrus’ eldest son, Cambyses, reigned for less than eight years. His greatest achievement was the
      conquest of Egypt. That he was favorably disposed toward the Jews is known from a Jewish document
      found in Egypt, but we have no evidence that he actively assisted the Jews in rebuilding their Temple.
      The short reign of the false Smerdis proved a great setback for the Jews. Under this king, described
      by Darius as a destroyer of temples, the work at Jerusalem was stopped. The stoppage may have been
      partly due to Samaritan enemies, for new foundations had to be laid as soon as stable conditions under
      the strong government of Darius I permitted resumption of the work. The era of Darius the Great was
      marked by prosperity and order. The Jews, like other nations, benefited from his wise and strong rule.
      Under the spiritual leadership of the prophets Haggai and Zechariah, they finished the Temple and
      dedicated it in the sixth regnal year of Darius, 515 B.C.
      An era of unrest began, however, when late in his reign Darius decided to invade Greece. From that
      time on the empire experienced repeated reverses in Greece, Egypt, and elsewhere that disturbed the
      internal peace and stability of the empire. The next two kings, Xerxes and Artaxerxes I, were weaklings,
      opportunists, and unstable in character, and owed their throne to the strong hand of powerful counselors.
      Disastrous campaigns in Greece and rebellions in Egypt and other parts of the empire caused great
      unrest and led to vacillating domestic and foreign policies.
      It was during a serious rebellion in Egypt (463–454 B.C.) that Ezra received major concessions for
      the Jews, whose good will Artaxerxes needed in this crucial period, since Judea lay athwart the highway
      to Egypt. Later, when the satrapy to which Judea belonged rebelled (after 450 B.C.), Artaxerxes
      apparently supported the supposedly loyal Samaritans under the erroneous assumption and fear that the
      Jews might join the rebellion. Accordingly Artaxerxes authorized the Samaritans to halt the rebuilding
      of the wall of Jerusalem, which had been in progress for some time. When order in the satrapy was
      restored, Nehemiah, a trusted Jewish court official, succeeded in obtaining a royal appointment as
      governor of Judea, and completed the rebuilding of the city wall. This he did under continuing threats of
      violence.
      He served as governor for two terms, and proved to be an able organizer and religious leader. He laid
      a comparatively solid political, social, and moral foundation that proved of great value in the turbulent
      times that followed.
      4. Theme. Ezra and Nehemiah are historical source books which record the outworking of the divine
      plan in the restoration of the Jews, whereby they were afforded another opportunity to cooperate with
      the eternal purposes and prove their right to exist as a nation. This record shows, furthermore, how the
      prophecies of Isaiah and Jeremiah were fulfilled, and provides invaluable source material by which other
      prophecies, those of Dan. 8 and 9, can securely be anchored to the facts of history.
      Ezra and Nehemiah illustrate, by a series of instructive examples, how a few people can do great
      things for God when led by God-fearing, sincere, unselfish, but fearless and determined leaders. These
      books contain much that edifies and that strengthens faith in the unfailing leadership of God.
    </text>
  </book>
  <book number ="28" name="HOSEA">
    <text>
      4. Theme. The dominant theme of the book of Hosea is the love of God for His erring children. The
      experiences through which the prophet passed in his own family life, and the feelings of his own heart
      toward his faithless wife, gave him a glimpse into the boundless depths of the Father’s love for His
      people.
      In the light of this divine love the terrible wickedness of the northern kingdom appears even blacker,
      and Hosea in no way excuses the people for their conduct. The prophet also paints in darkest hues the
      dreadful retributions that will fall upon Israel if they persist in their evil ways. These warnings are not
      threats, but are statements of fact, showing that punishment inevitably follows sin. However, through all
      his writing Hosea depicts the yearning love of God for His wayward people. The book is filled with
      appeals to repentance and messages of hope to those who will turn again to their loving Father.
    </text>
  </book>
  <book number ="30" name="AMOS">
    <text>
      4. Theme. The chief purpose of Amos was to call the attention of God’s people to their sins, and if
      possible to bring them to repentance. As the spirit of Paul was stirred at Athens when he saw how fully
      the city was given to idolatry, so Amos must have been stirred by the luxury and the sins he so vividly
      describes in detail. He rebuked the sins that sprang from material prosperity, the extravagances, the
      revelries, the debauchery of the rich, who were able to do this by oppressing the poor and by perverting
      judgment, through bribery and extortion. Amos gives more attention to the details and circumstances of
      iniquity than does Hosea. He is everywhere graphic, revealing transgression in the events of the daily
      life of the people. No evil practice seems to have escaped his notice. He counted it his duty to warn
      Israel, Judah, and the surrounding nations of the divine judgments that were sure to come upon them if
      they persisted in iniquity. However, he closes his book with a glorious picture of the ultimate triumph of
      righteousness over iniquity.
    </text>
  </book>
  <book number ="32" name="JONAH">
    <text>
      4. Theme. The book of Jonah is the only one of the twelve so-called Minor Prophets that is strictly
      narrative in form. It is an account of Jonah’s mission to the city of Nineveh to announce its speedy
      destruction because of its sins. The prophet entertains misgivings and perplexities as to his carrying out
      the charge of God to go to Nineveh. The very thought of journeying to this great metropolis, the
      difficulties and seeming impossibilities of the task, made him shrink from undertaking the divine
      commission and question its wisdom. Failing to rise to that strong faith that should have led him to
      realize that with the divine command came the divine power to accomplish it, Jonah sank into
      discouragement, dread, and despair (see PK 266). Knowing the loving-kindness and long-suffering of
      God. Jonah was also afraid that if he delivered the divine message and the heathen accepted it, the
      threatening doom he pronounced upon them would not come to pass. This would be a deep humiliation
      to him, as it thus turned out to be, and this he could not endure (ch. 4:1, 2). He at first disobeyed, but
      through a series of events was led to carry out the commission. The inhabitants of Nineveh repented, and
      for a time turned from their sins. Jonah was angry, but God justified His gracious dealings.
      Among the lessons taught by Jonah’s prophecy is the truth that God’s grace brings salvation to all
      (Titus 2:11), that it was indeed not confined to the Jews, but was also to be revealed among the heathen.
      God has “also to the Gentiles granted repentance unto life” (Acts 11:18). Like Peter (Acts 10), Jonah
      came to realize reluctantly that God was willing to receive those of every nation who turned to Him. By
      referring to “the men of Nineveh” who responded to Jonah’s call to repentance, Jesus condemned the
      pharisaical and prideful Jews of His day (see Matt. 12:41; Luke 11:32) and all others who, in their
      religious complacency and false sense of soul security, deceive themselves into thinking that they are the
      favored people of God, and thus assured of salvation.
      Jesus used the experience of Jonah in the sea as an illustration of His death and resurrection (Matt.
      12:39, 40). His reference to the book of Jonah establishes the veracity of the book.
      Expositors of the book of Jonah have followed two main lines of interpretation: (1) the historical,
      and (2) the allegorical. The second method has been adopted by those who deny the possibility of the
      miraculous elements in the book. They term the book variously a legend, a myth, a parable, or an
      allegory. For one who believes in miracles the second method of interpretation is both unnecessary and
      pointless.
    </text>
  </book>
  <book number ="33" name="MICAH">
    <text>
      4. Theme. Two main themes predominate: (1) the condemnation of the sins of the people and the
      consequent chastisement in captivity, and (2) the deliverance of Israel and the glory and gladness of the
      Messianic kingdom. Throughout the book of Micah threatening and promise, judgment and mercy,
      alternate.
      The prophecies of Micah and Isaiah have much in common. Inasmuch as the two prophets were
      contemporaries, and so had to deal with the same conditions and subjects, we can readily understand
      why their words and messages were so often similar.
      Though in the opening words of his book Micah tells us what “he saw concerning Samaria and
      Jerusalem,” his prophecy deals more with Judah than with Israel. Though the ten tribes had cut
      themselves off from Judah and from Jerusalem, the center of the worship of the Lord, they were still
      God’s people, and God was seeking to restore their allegiance to Him.
    </text>
  </book>
</bible>