<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<bible translation="New King James Version" language="English" id="NKJV-EN">
  <book number ="11" name="1 Kings">
    <text>
      1. Title. The present two books of Kings were originally one, known in Hebrew as Melakim,
      “Kings.” In the Hebrew Bible, Kings continued undivided until the time of the printed edition of
      Daniel Bomberg, 1516–17. The Greek translators of the LXX, who divided the “book of Samuel”
      into two books, also divided the “book of Kings” into two books, and treated the four as parts 1
      to 4 of “Kingdoms.”
      The title “Kings” indicates the contents of the books; our present first book of Kings gives
      the history of the Hebrew monarchs beginning with the death of David and the reign of
      Solomon and closing with the accession of Jehoram in Judah and Ahaziah in Israel. Second Kings
      begins with a continuation of the account of Ahaziah’s reign and closes with the end of the
      kingdom of Judah.
      4. Theme. Though the books of Kings present the history of the Hebrew rulers from the
      death of David and the reign of Solomon to the final destruction of the kingdoms of Israel and
      Judah, the primary purpose is not to present the facts of history for the sake of history. There is
      history, but it is presented with a purpose—to show how the experiences of the Hebrews relate
      to the plans and purposes of God. The object was not so much to write a detailed chronicle of
      the bald facts of history as to present the lessons of history. The compiler of these books had a
      deep religious motive and a very practical aim. The children of Israel were the people of God,
      and it was their task to fulfill the divine purpose and live out on earth the principles of the
      kingdom of heaven. Righteousness was to be the foundation for national prosperity. Sin could
      end only in ruin. If true to its divine mission, the nation would grow in strength and greatness. If
      kings and rulers failed to live up to the divine purpose, Israel as a people would perish. The
      nation could not exist without righteousness and without God.
      The amazing thing is that when the Israelites had failed as a nation and were face with utter
      and seemingly irretrievable ruin, someone found in the dark history of Israel’s sorrows and
      defeats something worth recording for generations to come. The lessons of Israel’s failure were
      to bring light and hope to the world. Upon the ashes of defeat there must yet be reared a new
      structure of success and victory. Israel might perish, but righteousness must not perish. If the
      lessons of Israel’s failure were learned, the world would yet find hope in God.
      The age when the book of Kings came into being was the age of the prophets. In the
      pronouncements of this book are to be found the courage and spiritual insight of the prophets,
      bringing home to the hearts of men lessons from God.
      The record of Kings begins with the glorious reign of Solomon, and the building of the
      Temple, with the nation virile and strong. It ends with the reign of a weak and infamous king,
      the Temple destroyed, and the land of Judah a desolate ruin. Yet this lesson of ruin was to
      rouse a new spirit of hope, and to focus attention upon a new and better age to come, with
      Israel ruled by its eternal King. “Lo, the days come, saith the Lord, that I will bring again the
      captivity of my people Israel and Judah, saith the Lord: and I will cause them to return to the
      land that I gave to their fathers, and they shall possess it” (Jer. 30:3). “They shall serve the Lord
      their God, and David their king, whom I will raise up unto them” (v. 9). “Jacob shall return, and
      shall be in rest, and be quiet, and none shall make him afraid” (v. 10). “I will give them one
      heart, and one way, that they may fear me for ever, for the good of them, and of their children
      after them: and I will make an everlasting covenant with them, that I will not turn away from
      them, to do them good; but I will put my fear in their hearts, that they shall not depart from
      me. Yea, I will rejoice over them to do them good, and I will plant them in this land” (ch. 32:39–
      41).
      Even though the primary purpose of Kings is not the presentation of history as such, it
      contains history of great importance and remarkable accuracy. There are items concerning the
      Hebrew rulers such as are never found in the annals of neighboring states. Secular annals of
      Israel’s neighbors were written to extol the king, to glorify him as builder, hunter, or statesman,
      to make public his acts of piety in the service of the gods, and to relate his exploits in war.
      Hebrew records as they have come down to us were to glorify not man but God. So we find in
      these records of Kings not only the outstanding accomplishments of the Israelite rulers but also
      their foibles and defeats.
      Kings contains items of historical importance not only concerning the kingdoms of Israel and
      Judah but concerning the nations round about. There are items of interest concerning Tyre and
      Egypt, ships of Tarshish going to Ophir for gold, Solomon’s navy at Ezion-geber on the shores of
      the Red Sea, the queen of Sheba’s coming to Jerusalem with a train of camels carrying spices
      and gold, Sennacherib’s being slain by his sons Adrammelech and Sharezer while worshiping in
      the house of his god, Syrian fears of Hittite kings, the tribute to Ahab of 100,000 lambs from
      Mesha, the sheepmaster king of Moab, the sending of the Egyptian forces of Tirhakah to harass
      the Assyrian hosts besieging Lachish and Libnah, Hiram’s importation of almug trees from Ophir
      to make pillars for the house of the Lord, the offering of the heir apparent as a burnt sacrifice
      upon a Moabite city wall to purchase the aid of the gods, Assyrian envoys speaking Aramaic and
      Hebrew in the 8th-7th centuries B.C., Zif and Ethanim and Bul as month names in the early
      history of Canaan—all interesting and vital ingredients of the basic stuff of which history is
      made.
      One of the outstanding features of the books of Kings is their basic chronological
      framework. Generally speaking, the kings are introduced in the order of their coming to the
      throne, regardless of whether they ruled in Israel or Judah. Two principal items of chronological
      information are given for each: (1) a synchronism, dating the beginning of the reign of a king of
      Judah in a specific year of the contemporary king of Israel, and vice versa, and (2) the length of
      each reign. Sometimes there are other time statements, such as intervals, regnal dates of
      events, or synchronisms between certain Hebrew reigns and those of other nations (see pp.
      135, 145).
      However, there are many difficulties in reconciling the figures given for Israel with those of
      Judah, and in harmonizing both with non-Biblical chronology. Even in a series of reigns
      beginning and ending together in Israel and Judah, the totals are not the same. Such difficulties
      have led some Biblical scholars to conclude that the chronology of the Hebrew kings has
      become hopelessly confused, through the centuries, because of copyists’ errors. The efforts of
      others to harmonize the data have resulted in numerous theories (though not wide in range),
      based mostly on varying conjectural revisions of the figures in an effort to reconcile them with
      non-Biblical chronology (see pp. 140, 143).
      Actually, the seeming discrepancies are due largely, if not altogether, to our lack of
      information as to the various technical methods of reckoning used in Bible times. Our
      increasing understanding of the basic chronological principles employed by the Hebrew scribes
      makes possible, through recent studies, the construction of a coherent pattern that aligns the
      reigns of both Hebrew kingdoms in harmony with practically all of the Biblical data, and with
      the generally accepted chronology of Assyria and Babylonia (see p. 143).
      The dates employed in this commentary for convenient reference (see tabulation on p. 77)
      are derived from chronological systems of the kings based on thorough studies, and are chosen
      as showing the greatest degree of harmony among the Biblical data and as coming nearest to a
      complete solution of the problem. They are presented only as a tentative outline, for it is
      possible that future discoveries throwing more light on those times may require more or less
      adjustment of this arrangement as a result of more exact knowledge of the chronology of the
      period.
    </text>
  </book>
  <book number ="8" name="Ruth">
    <text>
      1. Title. The book of Ruth forms an appendix to the book of Judges, and an introduction to
      the following two historical books of Samuel. It receives its title from the name of the person
      whose story it tells. Hebrew proper names have meanings. These are lost to the reader of the
      English translation of the Bible, because the translators have simply transliterated the proper
      names without attempting to give their meanings. Ruth was a Moabitish woman, and naturally
      her name is not Hebrew. The derivation and meaning of the name are uncertain, though some
      think it may be related to the verb ra‘ah, “to associate with,” and thus mean “friend,” or
      “friendship.”
      The book of Ruth gives us, not the story of romantic love, but of the reverential love of a
      young widow for the mother of her deceased husband. The love portrayed in the character of
      Ruth is of the purest, most unselfish, and extraordinary kind. Though a Moabitess, Ruth
      accepted Naomi’s faith as her own, and was rewarded by marriage to a Jewish nobleman, Boaz,
      by whom she became the ancestress of David, and thus, eventually, of Christ.
      4. Theme. There is narrative that is historic, and narrative that is epic. The word epic is
      applied to narrative whose appeal is not primarily to our sense of information but to our
      creative imagination and to the emotions. An epic is usually written in poetic form. A peculiarity
      of Hebrew poetry, however, is that its verse system is based on parallelism of thought rather
      than on exact meter and rhyme. This characteristic also appears, to a lesser extent, in Hebrew
      prose. Thus, in Hebrew, the classification of literature depends more on the nature of the
      thought than on the form of expression. Hebrew epics are portions of the national history fitted
      into their proper place in the narrative. Appreciation of the Bible as literature calls for a
      recognition of the different forms of narrative used by Bible writers.
      The chief purpose of the book of Ruth is to give information concerning the immediate
      ancestors of David, the greatest of the kings of Israel, the one in whose line was to come the
      Messiah. Christ is to be the eventual ruler of the kingdom of Israel after the spirit, the leader of
      the eternal theocracy. Christ spoke of His kingdom as the kingdom of heaven, to distinguish it
      from the kingdoms of this present world. The book of Ruth thus provides a cheering link in the
      inspired narrative of the kingdom Christ came to establish.
      At the same time Ruth presents a most appealing picture of the blessings of the ideal home.
      There are two institutions that have come down to us from before the fall of man—the Sabbath
      and the home. The home was established by God Himself on the sixth day of the first week of
      time, and the Sabbath on the seventh day of the same week. The Sabbath is not Jewish, for, as
      the Creator Himself said, “The sabbath was made for man, and not man for the sabbath” (Mark
      2:27). Both the Sabbath and the home have become the special objects of Satan’s attacks.
      The relationship of mother-in-law and daughter-in-law is a subject of amusement to many.
      But not so that of Ruth and her mother-in-law, Naomi. After a sojourn of ten years in the land
      of Moab, Naomi, whose husband and two sons had died, learned that a condition of plenty
      again prevailed in the land of Judah, and decided to return. Ruth, with a devotion that speaks
      almost as much for Naomi as it does for Ruth herself, broke all ties of home and kindred to
      accompany her. With a last look at the fertile fields of her homeland, Moab, and with an
      impassioned outburst to Naomi, “Thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God,” she
      entered a strange land, united with God’s true people, and became a worshiper of the God of
      heaven. This devotion to her mother-in-law resulted, finally, in her becoming one of the
      progenitors of David, the sweet psalmist of Israel; Solomon, the wisest of the sons of men;
      Zerubbabel, the later Moses; and the Messiah, the son of David. Finally the story is replete with
      superb examples of faith, piety, humility, industry, and loving-kindness revealed in the ordinary
      occurrences of life.
      Thus we have in the story of Ruth, not only a charming gem of Hebrew literature, but also a
      significant comment on a part of the genealogy of Christ (see on Matt. 1:4–6).
      Israel should have been prepared by a study of this narrative to understand God’s plan for
      the salvation of individuals of all nations who would do as Ruth the Moabitess did—accept the
      God whose character had been represented to them by His servants. It was God’s plan that
      many would thus be so transformed in character as to be prepared individually to become
      citizens of the eternal kingdom of Christ (see COL 290)
    </text>
  </book>
</bible>